Guide to the Tamiment Playhouse Photographs PHOTOS 041
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Playhouse Photographs
1920s-1987, (Bulk 1930s-1950s)
1930-1959
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Playhouse
Kolatch, Myron
PHOTOS 041
7.5 Linear Feet in 5 oversized flat boxes and one record carton.
The Tamiment Playhouse, located in Bushkill, Pennsylvania, was a prominent incubator of and a major creative outlet for theater, dance, film, and television in the mid-twentieth century, particularly for comedy. It nurtured many performers who later became famous, such as Danny Kaye, Carol Burnett, and Woody Allen. Much of the copious original material performed at Tamiment found its way to the professional stage, Broadway, and television. The Playhouse was part of Camp Tamiment, a summer resort for socialists and their families that opened in 1921. It began offering professional theatrical productions by the early 1930s, and closed after the season of 1960, victim of changes in the resort industry, trends and tastes in popular entertainment, and the gradual demise of Camp Tamiment itself.
(b&w; 8x 10 in.)
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Myron Kolatch on behalf of the Tamiment Playhouse in 1983. The accession number associated with this collection are 1983.003, 1983.006, and NPA.2005.031.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged chronologically within the chronological and scrapbook series; alphabetically within the topical and portrait series; there is no arrangement within the oversized series
The collection is organized into five series:
Missing Title
I. Chronological
II. Topical
III. Portraits, Individuals
IV. Scrapbooks
V. Oversized
Historical/Biographical Note
The Tamiment Playhouse, located in Bushkill, Pennsylvania, in the Pocono Mountains, was a prominent incubator of and a major creative outlet for theater, dance, film, and television in the mid-twentieth century, particularly for comedy. Actors such as Danny Kaye, Bea Arthur, Imogene Coca, Dick Shawn, and Carol Burnett, directors Max L. Liebman, Herb Ross, and Joe Layton, choreographers and dancers like Jerome Robbins, and Anita Alvarez, and writers Woody Allen and Neil Simon are a small sampling of the major entertainment figures nurtured at Camp Tamiment. The Playhouse was celebrated for its vibrant weekly original revues, filled with original music, songs, dances, and sketches. Much of this original material performed at Tamiment found its way to the professional stage, Broadway, and finally, television. "Your Show of Shows," one of the best-known programs of television's "Golden Age," had its origins in Tamiment productions.
The Playhouse had its home at Camp Tamiment, which began as a summer resort for socialists and their families. Less than two years after the Camp opened in 1921, campers and staff began to stage amateur theatricals, and a social hall for performances was built. By the early 1930s the Camp had hired a professional entertainment staff theatrical producer, Max Liebman. Out of this grew the professional theatrical productions that became the Tamiment Playhouse. The theater played its last season in 1960, when it was forced to close -- victim of changes in the resort industry, trends and tastes in popular entertainment, and the gradual demise of Camp Tamiment itself (which closed its doors in 1965).
Sources:
Martha LoMonaco. Every Week, A Broadway Review, the Tamiment Playhouse, 1921-1960(Greenwood Press, 1992)
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Camp Tamiment Photographs (Photographs 155); Tamiment Playhouse Archives (Tamiment 107)
Scope and Content Note
About two-thirds of the images in this collection are of Tamiment Playhouse productions or production-related activities, including from Your Show of Shows, and The Princess and the Pea, which later became the successful musical Once Upon a Mattress. The remainder of the images consist of a series of pages of photographs from scrapbooks. These photographs focus on Camp Tamiment -- its facilities, staff, and campers, from the 1920s through 1941 -- rather than the Playhouse. Although the original scrapbooks have been disassembled for preservation purposes, researchers are able to see how they were arranged originally, by examining a set of photocopies made of the scrapbook pages, arranged in their original order. Many photographs were also produced as postcards by photographers Lewis "Snappy" Goren and Seymour Fischer. There are also images of Ben Josephson and Bertha Mailly, respectively director and founder of Camp Tamiment.
Separated Materials
Separated from the Tamiment Playhouse Records (TAM 107)
Bushkill (Pa.); Summer resorts -- Pennsylvania.; Summer theater -- Pennsylvania.; Black-and-white photographs.; Mailly, Bertha -- |v Portraits; Tamiment Playhouse -- |v Pictorial works; Robbins, Jerome. -- |v Portraits; Camp Tamiment (Pa.) -- |v Pictorial works; Shawn, Dick. -- |v Portraits; Simon, Neil. -- |v Portraits; Layton, Joe, 1931-; Liebman, Max L. -- Portraits.; Kaye, Danny -- Portraits.; Coca, Imogene--Portraits.; Burnett, Carol--Portraits.; Arthur, Beatrice; Josephson, Ben, 1895-1980 -- |v Portraits; Fischer, Seymour.; Allen, Woody -- |v Portraits; Alvarez, Anita; Goren, Lewis M.; Kolatch, Myron
- Series I: Chronological
  - 1920s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1930s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1934 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1935 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1935 - "Meet the Social Staff" Brochure (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1939 - "Straw Hat Revue" Photos (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1940s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1940s? (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1940 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1941 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1942 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1943 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1943 - "Wainer Lee (Director) - 1943 Season (gift of Rita Wainer) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1944 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1945 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1946 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1947 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1948 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1948 - Cast/Crew Shot (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1948 Group Photo (and I.D.) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1949 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1949- "Admiral Broadway Revue" Photos (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1950's (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - 1950's- Color Transparencies-2 Scenes (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - 1950's - Curtis String Quartet (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - 1950s headshots - identified (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - 1950s headshots - unidentified (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - 1950 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - 1951 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - 1952 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - 1953 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - 1954 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - 1955 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - 1956 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - 1957 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - 1958 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - 1958 - "Princess and the Pea" photos (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - 1959 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - 1960's (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - 1960's - Constellation Room Entertainers (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - 1960 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - 1961 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - 1987 - Tamiment Resort in 1987 (7 snapshots with matching negatives) (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Series II: Topical
  - Concert Musicians; Quartets - Various Years, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Cross Country Revue/Liebman, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Playhouse, undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Television/Liebman - "Admiral Broadway"; "Your Show of Shows", undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Group shots, contact sheets, 1939, undated (Box 4, Folder 67-68)
- Series III: Portraits, Individuals
  - Allen, Woody - portrait, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Asch, Sholem (as guest), 1939 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Brody, Kaye, Coca, Fine (at piano), 1939 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Carroll, Pat, undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Green, Milton, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Hack, Monroe "Mo", by Lewis Goren, 1960 (Box Shared Tamiment 017, Folder 12)
  - Josephson, B.; Mrs. Mailly, etc. - Various, undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Kaye, Danny, undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Liebman, Max, undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Robbins, Jerome (Photos [photocopies] from Robbins Archive (personal)), undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Series IV: Scrapbooks, 1921-1941
  - Scrapbook G: 1921-1923 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Scrapbook H: 1927-1934 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Scrapbook I: 1929, 1931-1936 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Scrapbook J: 1937-1938 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Scrapbook K: 1938 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Scrapbook L: 1938-1941 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Scrapbook M: 1938-1939, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Photocopies of scrapbooks G through M (in original order), 1921-1941 (Box 5, Folder 68)
- Series V: Oversized
  - Mostly Tamiment Playhouse production stills and drawing of Tamiment Playhouse, 1950, undated (Box 6)